Finding Aid for Gordon Charles papers, 1934-2005
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Gordon Charles papers 1934-2005, 1953-1998
Charles, Gordon.
16 linear feet
06135 Aa 2
Gordon Charles wrote syndicated columns on travel and outdoor activities for local Michigan newspapers. His collection contains his journals, copies and clippings of his articles, his books, subject files, slides, photographs, and correspondence.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
This collection was donated by Gordon Charles (donor no. 9801 ) on October 31, 2006 and from his estate on May 31, 2007
Periodic additions to the records are not expected.
The collection is open to research.
Gordon Charles, born on August 23, 1920 in Salisbury, NC, wrote many articles on travel and outdoor activities. These syndicated columns were published in local Michigan newspapers such as the Traverse City Record-Eagle and The Flint Journal.
After Charles was born, the family moved from North Carolina to Cincinnati and then to Columbus, OH. The family finally settled in Traverse City, MI, where Charles attended and graduated high school. It was during this time that Charles started writing in journals detailing his day-to-day life. After high school he attended the Chapin School of Business. He then entered the Army where he worked in radio intelligence for 2 1/2 years. He then completed correspondence classes in journalism.
In 1945, Charles worked as a radio announcer, newscaster and commentator for WTCM in Traverse City, MI. He left WTCM for the Traverse City Record-Eagle in 1953 where he worked as a reporter and columnist. He began his weekly column "Outdoors with Gordie" at this time. In 1956, he became the outdoor editor for the paper.
In 1961, Charles moved to South Dakota to work as a Communications Specialist with the South Dakota Department of Game, Fish and Parks-Information and Education Series. He wrote news stories, magazine articles, and produced the weekly radio show "South Dakota Outdoors." In 1962, Charles was promoted to Chief of Information and Education for the Department.
Unable to pursue his own writing, he left South Dakota in 1965 and moved back to Michigan and became the editor for the Michigan Out-of-Doors. He continued to write articles for the Traverse City Record-Eagle until he retired in the mid-1990s. Charles died May 2, 2007.
The Gordon Charles papers contain his journals, copies and clippings of his articles, his books, subject files, slides, photographs, and correspondence related to his work as travel and outdoor activities writer for local Michigan newspapers. The papers are divided up into three series: Personal, Articles, and Subject Files.
Subjects:
Charles, Gordon.; Outdoor life--Michigan.; Outdoor writers--Michigan.; Travel writers--Michigan.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Archery--Michigan.; Deer hunting--Michigan.; Fishing--Michigan.; Lighthouses--Michigan.; Waterfalls--Michigan--Upper Peninsula.; Copper Harbor (Mich.); Fayette State Park (Mich.); Frankenmuth (Mich.); Gaylord (Mich.); Grayling (Mich.); Hartwick Pines State Park (Mich.); Indian River (Mich.); Isle Royale National Park (Mich.); Mackinac Island (Mich.); Fort Michilimackinac (Mackinaw City, Mich.); Old Mill Creek State Park (Mich.); Pictured Rocks National Lakeshore (Mich.); Pigeon River Country State Forest (Mich.); Porcupine Mountains Region (Mich.); Sleeping Bear Dunes National Lakeshore (Mich.); Traverse City (Mich.); Upper Peninsula (Mich.); Leland (Mich.)
Genre Terms:
Diaries.; Slides (photographs); Photographs.; Videotapes.
- Personal
  The Personal series includes journals, books, and various articles written about Charles. The series also contains his work and activities with the South Dakota Department of Game, Fish, and Parks and Family Information, including photographs and genealogical information.
  - Journals, 1934-1966, 16 volumes (Box 1)
  - Personal Information (Box 2)
  - Videotapes (VHS)
    - Rita Moretti Show and Eye on Michigan (interview about Egypt) (Box 2)
    - MOWA (Michigan Outdoor Writers Association) History 1996 (Box 2)
  - Awards and Honors (Box 2)
  - Correspondence (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, Fred Swaney (Box 2)
  - Family Materials
    - Family (Box 2)
    - E.F. Charles' (father) World War II Records and Civil Defense Pamphlets (Box 2)
    - Family Correspondence 1988-1995 (Box 2)
    - Genealogical Information, Charles Family (Box 2)
    - Genealogical Information, Huebner Family (Box 2)
    - Family Photographs/Slides (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous Photographs, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous Slides (Box 2)
  - Publications
    - A Boy, A Bike and Buster material and press clippings, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - A Guided to Sleeping Bear Dunes National Lakeshore, 1975 (Box 2)
    - Pigeon River Country, 1985 (Box 2)
    - Pocket Field Guide to Nature (Box 2)
    - Stalking and Capturing the Wild Pun, 2005 (Box 2)
  - South Dakota Department of Game, Fish, and Parks
    - Articles and Brochures 1961-1968 (Box 2)
    - Correspondence 1961-1966 (Box 2)
    - Personal Information 1961-1966 (Box 2)
    - Photos (Box 2)
    - Reports 1961-1965 (Box 2)
    - Scrapbook (Box 2)
  - Traverse City High School Class of 1939 (Box 3)
  - Trout Festival 1976 (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 3)
- Articles
  The Articles series includes outdoors and travel columns primarily published for the Traverse City Record-Eagle and for various Michigan local papers. The articles are divided up by year, by month, and by region based on Charles' original organizational scheme for these materials
  - "Outdoors with Gordie" Clippings
    - Index 1953 (Box 3)
    - 1953-1956 scattered, 3 folders (Box 3)
    - 1979-1989 scattered (Box 3)
    - 2003-2006, 4 folders (Box 3)
    - Undated Clippings (Box 3)
    - Proofs 1977-2007 scattered, 3 folders (Box 3)
  - "Outdoors with Gordie" Scrapbook Clippings
    - March 16-July 3, 1953 and photographs (Box 3)
    - January 2-December 31, 1959 (Box 3)
    - January 1-December 23, 1960 (Box 3)
    - September 2-December 31, 1960 (Box 3)
    - January 3-July 28, 1961 (Box 3)
  - Sportsman's Notebook (Box 4)
    - 1948 (Box 4)
  - Traverse City Record-Eagle: Outdoors Section
    - 1956 (Box 4)
    - 1957, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - 1958, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - 1959, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - 1960, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - 1961, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Traverse City Record-Eagle: Travel News
    - 1985 (Box 4)
    - 1986 (Box 4)
    - 1987 (Box 4)
    - 1987-1988 (Box 5)
    - 1988-1989 (Box 5)
    - 1990-1999 (Box 5)
  - Traverse City Record-Eagle: Travel News by Region
    - Africa and Asia (Box 5)
    - Europe (Box 5)
    - Asia and the Pacific (Box 5)
    - North America (Box 5)
    - South America and the Caribbean (Box 5)
  - Traverse City Record-Eagle: Travel News by Month, 1994-1998
    - January (Box 5)
    - February (Box 5)
    - March (Box 5)
    - April (Box 5)
    - May (Box 5)
    - June (Box 5)
    - July (Box 5)
    - August (Box 5)
    - September (Box 5)
    - October (Box 5)
    - November (Box 5)
    - December (Box 5)
  - Traverse City Record-Eagle: Articles, book binding copy, 1983-1991 (Box 6)
  - Detroit Sunday Times, 1957-1960 (Box 6)
  - The Flint Journal, 1961 (Box 6)
  - Grand Rapids Pioneer, 1958, 1960 (Box 6)
  - Michigan Sportsman, Winter 1959-Spring 1961 (Box 6)
  - Northwestern Michigan Sportsman, March 1959-June 1961 (Box 6)
  - Ottaway News Service Tearsheets, 1986-1987 (Box 6)
  - Woods-n-Water News, 1999-2006, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous, articles and photographs 1954-1992, 8 folders (Box 6)
  - Story Ideas (Box 6)
- Subject Files
  The Subject Files series is further divided by Subject and Location. These include files on a number of subjects related to the outdoors. The Location subseries includes Charles' files on a number of locations, local and international. Many of these files are related to his work as a Travel Writer and include articles and slides related to various locales. There are also a number of Michigan cities, parks, outdoor activities, wildlife, and man-made features such as lighthouses and dams.
  - By Subject
    - Albinos (Box 7)
    - American River Tours (ARTA) (Box 7)
    - Archery (Box 7)
    - Artwork (Box 7)
    - Audubon (Box 7)
    - B-Various (Box 7)
    - Bear Hunt Photos (Box 7)
    - Berries (Box 7)
    - Bigfoot (Box 7)
    - Biking and Hiking (Box 7)
    - Birds
      - Features and Pictures (Box 7)
      - Feeding (Box 7)
      - Series (Box 7)
    - Bittern (Box 7)
    - Bluebirds (Box 7)
    - Bluejays (Box 7)
    - Boardman River Dams (Box 7)
    - Boating Magazines (Box 7)
    - Bowhunting (Box 7)
    - Butterflies and Moths (Box 7)
    - Camping, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Canoeing, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Chickadees (Box 7)
    - Clams (Box 7)
    - Compasses/Getting Lost/Survival (Box 7)
    - Cormorants (Box 7)
    - Cottontail Rabbit (Box 7)
    - Coyotes (Box 7)
    - Cranes (Box 7)
    - Crayfish (Box 7)
    - Dams and Bridges (Box 7)
    - Deer, South Fox Island and North and South Manitou Island, 2 folders (Box 8)
    - Doves and Pigeons (Box 8)
    - Ducks
      - Ducks, 2 folders (Box 8)
      - Tree Ducks (Box 8)
      - Duck Photos (Box 8)
    - Eagles, 2 folders (Box 8)
    - Earthworms
      - Earthworms (Box 8)
      - As Cuisine (Box 8)
    - Edible Plants (Box 8)
    - Elgee Cartoons (Box 8)
    - Endangered Wildlife (Box 8)
    - Features (Box 8)
    - Fish
      - General (Box 8)
      - Slides, 2 folders (Box 8)
    - Frogs (Box 9)
    - Geese, 3 folders (Box 9)
    - Grackle (Box 9)
    - Grasshoppers (as bait) (Box 9)
    - Grayling (Box 9)
    - Great Blue Heron (Box 9)
    - Grosbeaks (Box 9)
    - Grouse
      - Black Grouse (Box 9)
      - Ruffed Grouse, 3 folders (Box 9)
      - Sharptailed Grouse (Box 9)
      - Grouse Society (Box 9)
    - Gulls (Box 9)
    - Guns, 2 folders (Box 9)
    - Hawks (Box 9)
    - Hummingbirds (Box 9)
    - Ice Fishing (Box 9)
    - Insects, 2 folders (Box 9)
    - Inuit (Box 9)
    - Kellum, Ford (Box 9)
    - Keweenaw Peninsula (Box 9)
    - Killdeer (Box 9)
    - Kingfisher (Box 10)
    - Kirtland's Warbler (Box 10)
    - Lawrence, Rod (Box 10)
    - Lemmings (Box 10)
    - Lievense, Stan (Box 10)
    - Lighthouses (Box 10)
    - Lizards (Box 10)
    - Log Drive-Ontario (Box 10)
    - Loon (Box 10)
    - M-Various (Box 10)
    - Martins (Box 10)
    - Metal Detecting (Box 10)
    - Migration (Box 10)
    - MOWA (Michigan Outdoor Writers Association), 3 folders (Box 10)
    - Mudpuppies (Box 10)
    - Mushrooms
      - Mushrooms (Box 10)
      - Morels (Box 10)
    - Mosquitoes, Biting Pests (Box 10)
    - Muzzleloaders (Box 10)
    - National Trout Festival (Box 10)
    - Nature (Box 10)
    - Nighthawks (Box 10)
    - Nuthatches (Box 10)
    - Nuts (Box 10)
    - Oil (Box 10)
    - Ospreys (Box 10)
    - Owls
      - Owls (Box 10)
      - Barn Own (Box 10)
      - Great Horned Owl (Box 10)
      - Screech Owl (Box 10)
      - Snowy Owl (Box 10)
    - Pelicans (Box 10)
    - Peregrine Falcon (Box 11)
    - Photography (Box 11)
    - Pileated Woodpecker (Box 11)
    - Poisonous Plants (Box 11)
    - Ravens (Box 11)
    - Recipes (Box 11)
    - Robin (Box 11)
    - Rocks (Box 11)
    - Salmon and Trout (Box 11)
    - SCUBA (Box 11)
    - Shelley, Howard (Box 11)
    - Shooting Preserves (Box 11)
    - Shorebirds (Box 11)
    - Shrike (Box 11)
    - Skin Divers (Box 11)
    - Snails (Box 11)
    - Snakes (Box 11)
    - Snowshoes (Box 11)
    - Songbirds (Box 11)
    - Sparrows (Box 11)
    - Stamps (Box 11)
    - Starlings (Box 11)
    - Survival by Camping (Box 11)
    - Swans, 2 folders (Box 11)
    - Terns (Box 11)
    - Toads (Box 11)
    - Trapping (Box 11)
    - Travel Writers, Midwest (Box 11)
    - Trees
      - Trees, 2 folders (Box 12)
      - Ash (Box 12)
      - Aspen (Box 12)
      - Beech & Birch (Box 12)
      - Chestnut (Box 12)
      - Elm (Box 12)
      - Hemlock (Box 12)
      - Maples (Box 12)
      - Pines (Box 12)
      - Oak (Box 12)
      - Tamarack (Box 12)
    - Turkey Buzzards (Box 12)
    - Turtles (Box 12)
    - Waterfalls, Upper Peninsula (Box 12)
    - Whooping Cranes (Box 12)
    - Woodpeckers (Box 12)
  - By Location
    - Alaska, 5 folders (Box 12)
    - Alberta (Box 13)
    - Apostle Islands (Box 13)
    - Aruba (Box 13)
    - Australia (Box 13)
    - Bahamas (Box 13)
    - Barbados and Grenada (Box 13)
    - British Columbia (Box 13)
    - California-San Francisco (Box 13)
    - Caribbean (Box 13)
    - Cartagena, Columbia (Box 13)
    - Chicago (Box 13)
    - China, 2 folders (Box 13)
    - Ecuador (Box 13)
    - Eurail, 2 folders (Box 13)
    - Florida, 2 folders (Box 13)
    - Georgia (Box 13)
    - Germany (Box 13)
    - Grand Cayman Island (Box 13)
    - Iceland and Greenland (Box 13)
    - Indiana (Box 13)
    - Israel (Box 13)
    - Jamaica (Box 13)
    - Kentucky, 2 folders (Box 14)
    - Kenya (Box 14)
    - Lake Huron (Box 14)
    - Lake Michigan (Box 14)
    - Lake Superior Circle Tour, 3 folders (Box 14)
    - Louisiana (Box 14)
    - Maine (Box 14)
    - Manitoba (Box 14)
    - Manitoulin Island, Ontario (Box 14)
    - Mexico, 2 folders (Box 14)
    - Michigan
      - Copper Harbor (Box 14)
      - Detroit (Box 14)
      - Fayette State Park (Box 14)
      - Frankenmuth (Box 14)
      - Gaylord (Box 14)
      - Grayling (Box 14)
      - Hartwick Pines State Park (Box 14)
      - Indian River (Box 14)
      - Isle Royale National Park (Box 14)
      - Leelanau (Box 14)
      - Leelanau County (Box 14)
      - Mackinac Island (Box 14)
      - Mackinac Island, Ft. Michilimackinac and Parade (Box 14)
      - Old Mill Park (Box 14)
      - Pictured Rocks National Lakeshore (Box 14)
      - Pigeon River Country, 4 folders (Box 15)
      - Porcupine Mountains (Box 15)
      - Sleeping Bear Dunes National Park and Leland, MI (Box 15)
      - Traverse City Area (Box 15)
      - Upper Peninsula, 2 folders (Box 15)
      - Michigan Travel Stories (Box 15)
    - Minnesota (Box 15)
    - Mississippi (Box 15)
    - Missouri Morocco, 2 folders (Box 15)
    - M/V Regent Sea Cruise (Box 15)
    - Nebraska (Box 15)
    - Neultin/Snowbird Lakes (Northwest Territories) (Box 15)
    - Nevada (Box 15)
    - New York (Box 15)
    - New Zealand, 2 folders (Box 15)
    - North and South Carolina (Box 15)
    - Northwest Territories, Canada, 2 folders (Box 16)
    - Ohio (Box 16)
    - Ontario, 2 folders (Box 16)
    - Oregon (Box 16)
    - Panama (Box 16)
    - Paris, France (Box 16)
    - Peru, 2 folders (Box 16)
    - Philippines (Box 16)
    - Portugal (Box 16)
    - Prince Edward Island, 2 folders (Box 16)
    - Scotland (Box 16)
    - St. Joseph Island, Ontario (Box 16)
    - South Pacific (Box 16)
    - Spain (Box 16)
    - Switzerland (Box 16)
    - Tennessee (Box 16)
    - Toronto and Niagara Falls (Box 16)
    - Taiwan (Box 16)
    - Utah (Box 16)
    - Vancouver, British Columbia, 2 folders (Box 16)
    - Wisconsin, 2 folders (Box 16)
    - Yugoslavia (Box 16)
    - Yukon Territory (Box 16)